Malcolm S. Knowles Papers
Malcolm S. Knowles Papers
- Printed material
  - Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (HEW)
    - Office of Education, Division of Adult and Vocational Research, 1966; project summaries (Box 48)
    - Report of the secretary, 1963 (Box 48)
  - United States Executive Office of the President, Office of Consumer Affairs, Consumer education for adults, 1971-1972 (Box 48)
  - United States House of Representatives Committee on Post Office and Civil Service, Subcommittee on Manpower and Civil Service, 1967; report (Box 48)
  - United States President's Committee on Education Beyond the High School, 1956; 1957; interim reports (Box 48)
  - University in lifelong education, by Joseph Rovan, 1978 (Box 48)
  - University Microfilms, Inc., Dissertations of the 60's catalog, 1964 (Box 48)
  - University of British Columbia Faculty of Education, Journal of education, no. 18, 1971 (Box 48)
  - University of Chicago, Continuing education report, no. 2, 1965 (Box 48)
  - University of Connecticut Center for Black Studies, Competencies of adult educators, 1961 (Box 48)
  - University of Georgia Center for Continuing Education, 1975; proposal (Box 48)
  - University of Kentucky College of Library Science, Office for Continuing Education, 1975; proposal (Box 48)
  - University of North Carolina School of Medicine, Trends in medical education, no. 12, 1976 (Box 48)
  - University of Oklahoma College of Liberal Studies, 1978; advisor's notebook (Box 48)
  - University of Pittsburgh School of Education, 1979; proposal (Box 48)
  - University of South Carolina College of Engineering, Institute for advanced professional studies in engineering, 1980 (Box 48)
  - University preparation for community college education, by Eugene E. DuBois (Box 48)
  - Viewpoints, vol. 49, no. 5, 1973 (Box 49)
  - Volkshochschulen in the Federal Republic of Germany and West Berlin, undated (Box 49)
  - Volunteer administration, vol. 10, no. 2, 1977 (Box 49)
  - Volunteer papers (Box 49)
  - Wakati Wa Furaha: evaluation of a radio study group campaign, by Budd L. Hall, 1973 (Box 49)
  - Wayne County (MI) Intermediate School District, Adult education staff development plan, 1978-1979 (Box 49)
  - WGBH-TV Boston University, Dynamics of leadership, 1961 (Box 49)
  - What does it take for faculty development to make a difference?, by Karen J. Connell, Jean M. Alberti and Zdzislaw H. Piotrowski, 1976-1977 (Box 49)
  - What dulls my mind and saps my will steals life, by Grace M. Healy, 1973 (Box 49)
  - Why teach the humanities to adult basic education students?, ed. by Donald W. Mocker and William C. Jones, 1975 (Box 49)
  - Wilmington morning star, 1976 (Box 49)
  - World Education proposal, 1971 (Box 49)
  - Yokefellow Institute, Inc., 1974; grant proposal (Box 49)
  - Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA)
    - National Council Bulletin, vol. 36, no. 5, 1962 (Box 49)
    - National Council Design for Training, 1967 (Box 49)
    - Organization Development Program bulletins, 1962-1965 (Box 49)
    - Organization Development Program training priorities, 1960's (Box 49)
    - Report on the evaluation of participants in the in-residence study phase of the 2nd unit of the experimental association program for professional development in YMCA secretaryship, 1967 (Box 49)
    - YMCA at work in the inner city, undated (Box 49)
  - YMCA of Canada National Council, Hi-Y tomorrow, undated (Box 49)
  - Your New England Foundation for Continuing Dental Education, undated; manual (Box 49)
- Published material
  - Adult basic education teacher competency inventory, by Donald W. Mocker, James D. Peebles, Lorraine M. Zinn, Gordon Ault, and Vera S. Maass, 1974 (Box 50)
  - Adult education activities for public libraries, by Carl Thomsen, Edward Sydney and Miriam D. Tompkins, 1950 (Box 50)
  - Adult education activities in public libraries, by Helen Lyman Smith, 1954 (Box 50)
  - Adult education in Liberia, by Robert M. Smith, 1965 (Box 50)
  - Adult education in Sweden, by Paul Bergevin, 1961 (Box 50)
  - Adult learning, by Irving Lorger, Gale Jensen, Leland P. Bradford, and Max Birbaum, 1965 (Box 50)
  - Algonquin College of Applied Arts & Technology-Teachers of Adults Program
    - Education development officer's manual, 1977 (Box 50)
    - Handbook, 1977 (Box 50)
    - Resource booklets, no. 5-8, 1977 (Box 50)
  - American Society for Training and Development, 1974; professional development manual (Box 50)
  - Approach to informal adult education, ed. by Alden Eberly, 1961 (Box 50)
  - Automated training design: new dimension in adult education, 1965 (Box 50)
  - Bibliographies of career-related materials, 1975 (Box 51)
  - Citizen participation in federal programs, by Hans B.C. Spiegel, 1971 (Box 51)
  - Communication and status: dynamics of a research center, by Alfred G. Smith, 1966 (Box 51)
  - Continuing education as a national capital investment, by Herbert E. Striner, 1971 (Box 51)
  - Cooperative Assessment of Experiential Learning (CAEL)
    - Assessing prior learning, by Joan Knapp, 1977 (Box 51)
    - Compendium of assessment techniques, by Joan Knapp and Amiel Sharon, 1975 (Box 51)
    - Learning and assessing interpersonal competence - CAEL student guide, by Paul Breen, Thomas F. Donlon and Urban Whitaker, 1977 (Box 51)
    - Principles of good practice in assessing experiential learning, by Warren W. Willingham, 1977 (Box 51)
    - Teaching and assessing interpersonal competence - CAEL handbook, by Paul Breen, Thomas F. Donlon and Urban Whitaker, 1977 (Box 51)
  - Coping with problems in meeting training needs for cross-cultural international training, by Milton J. Feldman, 1977 (Box 51)
  - Council for the Advancement of Experiential Learning, Self-directed educator - CAEL syllabus, by Mark Cheren, 1979 (Box 51)
  - Critical requirements for training directors, by Donald W. Devine, 1962 (Box 51)
  - Decision-making in the planning and implementation of instruction in adult basic education, by Robert E. Snyder, 1971 (Box 51)
  - Dynamic management education, by Allen A. Zoll, 1966; 3 folders (Box 51, 52)
  - Dynamics of participative groups, by J.R. Gobb, Grace N. Platts and Lorraine F. Miller, 1951 (Box 52)
  - Education in industry, by Seymour Lusterman, 1977 (Box 52)
  - Educational experience, by Robert Redfield, 1955 (Box 52)
  - Effective use of training aids, 1948 (Box 52)
  - Expand your life, by Allen Tough, 1980 (Box 52)
  - Group dynamics and social action, by Kenneth D. Benne, Leland P. Bradford and Ronald Lippitt, 1950 (Box 52)
  - Guidance function and counseling roles in an adult education program, by Violet M. Malone, Ph.D. and Mary Ann Diller, Ph.D., 1978 (Box 52)
  - Guide to local politics, by David A. Booth, 1961 (Box 52)
  - General Electric Career Development Program, 1972; career planning journal, manager's manual; 2 folders (Box 52)
  - Handbook for data processing educators, by Roger Sullivan, 1979 (Box 52)
  - How adults can learn more faster, 1961 (Box 52)
  - How to make and interpret functional organization charts, by John J. Furia, Ph.D., 1943 (Box 52)
  - How to select, train and use volunteers in the school, by Rosa Alexander Harris, 1985 (Box 52)
  - In-service education in adult basic education, by Alan B. Knox, 1971 (Box 52)
  - International University Consortium
    - Adult years: continuity and change, 1984-1985 (Box 52)
    - Exploring language: thinking, writing, communicating, 2nd ed., by Marilyn Majeska, 1985 (Box 52)
  - Issues in nontraditional study, v.1, ed. by John R. Valley and I. Bruce Hamilton, 1976 (Box 52)
  - Jesness inventory, by Carl F. Jesness, Ph.D., 1962 (Box 52)
  - Keys to creative work with volunteers, by Chama A. Lewis, CAVS and Leo F. Johnson, Ed.D., 1977 (Box 52)
  - Leadership in the 80's: essays on higher education, by Chris Argyris and Richard M. Cyert, 1980 (Box 53)
  - Leadership influence matrix (LIM): conceptual approach, by Capt. L.I. Moore, 1975 (Box 53)
  - Leisure counseling techniques, by Patsy B. Edwards, 1975 (Box 53)
  - Library staff development profile pages, by Barbara Conroy, 1979 (Box 53)
  - Life transitions reader, by Vivian Rogers McCoy, Colleen Ryan, Robin Suton, and Nancy Winn, 1980 (Box 53)
  - Making the transition to training, by Leah R. Humlie and Patricia A. Denman, M.A., 1984 (Box 53)
  - McBer and Company
    - Learning style inventory, by David A. Kolb, 1976 (Box 53)
    - Personal learning guide, 1979 (Box 53)
  - Metropolitan State University, Individualized educational planning, 1982 (Box 53)
  - National University Consortium, Systems Organization
    - Faculty and administrative materials, 1982 (Box 53)
    - Student course guide, 1983 (Box 53)
  - Opinions of school superintendents on adult education, by National Education Association-Research Division, 1964 (Box 53)
  - Personality style and sociometric choice, by Jeanne Watson Eisenstadt, 1969 (Box 53)
  - Physiological factors in adult learning and instruction, by Coolie Verner and Catherine V. Davison, 1971 (Box 53)
  - Presenter's guide to conferences, by Chip Bell and Frederic Margolis, 1980 (Box 53)
  - Psychology as a profession, by Robert I. Watson, 1954 (Box 53)
  - Recommendations on credentializing educational accomplishment, by Task Force on Educational Credit and Credentials, 1978 (Box 53)
  - Retirement Planning Associates, Inc., Retirement planning manual, by Katherine A. Grant and Betty H. Wiser, 1981 (Box 53)
  - Sales psychology, by J.T. Hart, 1984 (Box 53)
  - Social groups, roles and leadership: introduction to the concepts, by Donald W. Olmsted, 1961 (Box 54)
  - Standard Oil Company, Summary report of the early identification of management potential research project in Standard Oil Company (New Jersey) and affiliated companies, 1961 (Box 54)
  - Supervisory inventories and temporary manual, by Donald L. Kirkpatrick, Ph.D., 1965 (Box 54)
  - Survey of continuing education activities for engineers and scientists, by John P. Klus and Judy A. Jones, 1978 (Box 54)
  - Synthesis of selected manuscripts about the education of adults in the United States, by James R. Broschart, 1976 (Box 54)
  - Taking your meetings out of the doldrums, by Eva Schindler-Rainman, Ronald Lippitt and Jack Cole, 1975 (Box 54)
  - Training and development handbook, 2nd ed., ed. by Robert L. Craig, 1979 (Box 54)
  - Treasury of techniques for teaching adults, 1964; 1973 (Box 54)
  - University adult education in the later 20th century, 1970 (Box 54)
  - Voluntary action and social problems, compiled and ed. by David Horton Smith and Richard D. Reddy, 1971 (Box 54)
  - Write your own job description, by Michael Frayling, 1974 (Box 54)
- Scrapbooks
  - Boston YMCA years, 1940-1943 (Box 54)
  - Chicago YMCA years, 1946-1947 (Box 54)
  - Chicago YMCA years, 1948-1949 (Box 55)
  - College years, 1930-1935 (Box 55)
  - Detroit YMCA years, 1943-1944 (Box 55)
  - National Youth Administration years, 1935-1940 (Box 56)
  - Navy years, 1944-1946 (Box 56)
- Speeches
  - Conference on extension activities, address excerpts by Paul A. Miller, Asst. Sec. for Ed. in Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1966 (Box 56)
  - Founder's Day address at Boston University, 1957 (Box 56)
  - Fund for Adult Education speech on liberal adult education, 1956 (Box 56)
  - "Group process in adult education," by Malcolm S. Knowles, 1952 (Box 56)
  - "Innovations in education and training of health manpower," by Daniel S. Schechter, 1966 (Box 56)
  - "Is lifelong adult education a guarantee of permanent inadequacy?" by John Ohliger, 1974 (Box 56)
  - "Man's confidence in himself," by Malcolm S. Knowles, 1955 (Box 56)
  - National Defense University address to faculty, students and staff, by General Pustay, 1981 (Box 56)
  - "Planning for lifelong learning," by Malcolm S. Knowles, 1961 (Box 56)
  - "Relentless verity: education for being-becoming-belonging," by James Robbins Kidd, 1973 (Box 56)
  - Syracuse University conference on instruction learning, theory speeches, 1956 (Box 56)
  - "What is education, really? And what is the Church's role in it?" by Malcolm S. Knowles, 1960 (Box 56)
  - "Why adults participate in education," by Gordon G. Darkenwald, 1977 (Box 56)
- Workshop files
  - Adult Learning Programs of Alaska
    - Alaskan workshops, 1981 (Box 56)
    - Changing Alaska, 1980 (Box 56)
  - Aid Association for Lutherans, 1981; volunteer trainer network training event (Box 56)
  - Algonquin College of Applied Arts & Technology, 1973-1974 (Box 56)
  - American Association of University Women, 1968- 1969; community leadership training program (Box 56)
  - American Public Power Association, 1967; management education program (Box 56)
  - American Society for Training and Development (ASTD)
    - Institute for the training professional, 1969 (Box 56)
    - Southern Minnesota chapter, Andragogical approach to training, 1974 (Box 56)
  - Antioch College human resources, 1975 (Box 57)
  - Archdiocese of Chicago Center for Adult Learning
    - Assumptions and tactics of adult education, 1972 (Box 57)
    - Programming and evaluation in adult education, 1972 (Box 57)
  - Archdiocese of Detroit Institute for Continuing Education, 1977; expansion workshops (Box 57)
  - Archdiocese of St. Paul and Minneapolis, MN, Motivating adults to learn, 1977 (Box 57)
  - Association of Nurses of the Province of Quebec, 1970; workshop on in-service education (Box 57)
  - Board of Education, Toronto, Canada, Helping adults learn, 1970 (Box 57)
  - Boston University School of Nursing, 1974; workshop on institutional change (Box 57)
  - Brazil, state universities, 1977; faculty development (Box 57)
  - Burlington Industries Inc., 1977; training managers meeting (Box 57)
  - Burlington (VT) Public Schools, Teamwork in educational leadership, 1967 (Box 57)
  - Cambridge House Center for Human Potential, Planning for change, 1970 (Box 57)
  - Canada Public Service Commission, Bureau of Staff Development and Training, 1974-1975; development and training workshops (Box 57)
  - College of DuPage Extension College, 1974; in-service program (Box 57)
  - Columbia University School of Public Health and Administrative Medicine
    - Management development workshops, 1965-1967 (Box 57)
    - Seminars for executive directors of state hospital associations, 1969 (Box 57)
  - Connecticut Hospital Association, 1970-1972 (Box 58)
  - Connecticut Nurses' Association, 1968; professional development seminar (Box 58)
  - Cornell University, New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations, 1966; consultation (Box 58)
  - Council for the Advancement of Experiential Learning (CAEL), 1979-1980; professional development workshops (Box 58)
  - Curry College, 1974; faculty workshop (Box 58)
  - Cutler-Hammer, 1971; marketing management seminar (Box 58)
  - Development Dimensions, Inc., Advanced workshop for interaction management administration, 1977 (Box 58)
  - Diocese of Springfield, MA Office of Religious Education, Day of enrichment, 1974 (Box 58)
  - Emmanuel College Training Center in Religious Education, Theory and practice of andragogy, 1974 (Box 58)
  - Florida State University College of Education, Division of Educational Management Systems
    - Adult education seminars, 1977 (Box 58)
    - National institute on resource utilization and development in adult basic education, 1970 (Box 58)
  - Ford Motor Company workshop, 1974 (Box 58)
  - General Electric Company
    - Manager development course, 1969 (Box 58)
    - Management development institute, 1970-1971; includes career development and manpower evaluation; 2 folders (Box 58)
  - General Motors Corporation, Chevrolet Motor Division, 1963; communication workshops (Box 58)
  - George Washington University Center for Professional Development, 1980-1981; professional development and training programs (Box 58)
  - Georgia State University Institute for Chief State School Officers, eak use of peak years, 1975 (Box 58)
  - Goddard College, Helping adults learn workshop, 1970 (Box 59)
  - H.P. Hood and Sons, 1969-1970; training workshops (Box 59)
  - International Business Machines (IBM)
    - Education staff training program, 1968-1969 (Box 59)
    - Management development instructor techniques school, 1971-1974; 1977 (Box 59)
    - Manager development workshops, 1969-1970 (Box 59)
    - Presentations on management and adult learning, and creativity, 1968 (Box 59)
  - Inter-university forum for educators in community psychiatry, 1967-1970 (Box 59)
  - Kansas State University Adult Education Center, Self-directed learning institute, 1975 (Box 59)
  - Loyola College Evening Division, 1973-1974; andragogy workshops (Box 59)
  - Maine
    - Department of Health and Welfare, Division of Child Welfare, 1969; staff development (Box 59)
    - York County Council on Aging, Inc., 1969; workshops (Box 59)
  - Management Manpower Developers, Adult learning and human resources development, 1982 (Box 59)
  - Marymount College of Kansas, Continuing education for health professionals, 1973 (Box 59)
  - Massachusetts Nurses Association, Designing better in-service education programs, 1969 (Box 59)
  - McMaster University School of Nursing, 1976-1977; self-directed and contract learning workshops (Box 59)
  - Mercyhurst College, 1975; faculty workshops (Box 59)
  - Montana State University College of Education, Organization and administration of adult education, 1970 (Box 59)
  - Montana State University Workshop on Chinese area studies for high school teachers in Montana State, undated (Box 59)
  - National Academy of Health Inservice Education workshop, 1971 (Box 59)
  - National Association of Social Workers
    - Workshop on community development in the United States, 1962 (Box 59)
    - Workshop on continuing education, 1968 (Box 59)
  - National Catholic Educational Association workshop, 1972 (Box 59)
  - National Drug Abuse Training Center, 1973; staff development (Box 60)
  - National Education Association
    - National Training Laboratories, 3rd annual national training laboratories for educators, 1961 (Box 60)
    - Research Center for Group Dynamics, MIT, 1st national training laboratory on group development, 1947 (Box 60)
  - National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH) Continuing Education Branch, 1971; interdisciplinary workshop (Box 60)
  - National workshop on individualized education, 1977 (Box 60)
  - Needham (MA) Public Schools, 1970; professional self-improvement workshop (Box 60)
  - New Hampshire State Department of Education, 1972; staff development (Box 60)
  - New Jersey Adult Education Association, Professional development program for continuing education leaders, 1968 (Box 60)
  - Newton (MA) Public Schools - Bigelow Junior High School, Faculty seminar in group and interpersonal relations, 1967 (Box 60)
  - Newton (MA) Unified School District No. 373, 9th Annual summer workshop, 1972 (Box 60)
  - North Carolina State University Department of Adult and Community College Education, Community college business management institute, 1974 (Box 60)
  - Northeastern University Center for Continuing Education, Professional management of volunteer programs, 1973 (Box 60)
  - Northland Open University Canadian School of Management, Self-directed learning, 1982 (Box 60)
  - NTL Institute for Applied Behavioral Sciences - American Society for Training and Development, Professional development workshop on organizational sexism, 1971 (Box 60)
  - Ohio Nurses Association, adult learner workshop (Box 60)
  - Ontario Association for Continuing Education (OISE), Post-secondary education workshop, 1971 (Box 60)
  - Oregon State University - School of Education Directing adult learning, 1971 (Box 61)
  - Organizational Renewal, Inc., Implementing the organization renewal process, 1970 (Box 61)
  - Pan American World Airways, 1971; staff training workshop (Box 61)
  - Polaroid Corporation, Adult learning and skills development, 1969 (Box 61)
  - Prairie View Mental Health Center
    - Humanizing education, 1971 (Box 61)
    - In search of values, 1971 (Box 61)
  - Project Associates, Inc., Staff specialist as an internal consultant program, 1972 (Box 61)
  - Providence (RI) Public Schools Adult Education Department, Invitational workshop in adult education, 1968 (Box 61)
  - Quebec Camping Association, Camp team seminar, 1974 (Box 61)
  - Quinsigamond Community College
    - Faculty development, 1970-1971 (Box 61)
    - 2nd annual all-Worcester County gerontological institute, 1974 (Box 61)
  - Regional Adult Education Center, 1979; rural education workshop (Box 61)
  - Research training institute, 1967 (Box 61)
  - Reservation agents' workshop, 1970 (Box 61)
  - Roche Laboratory, Anxiety colloquium, 1972 (Box 61)
  - St. Andrews Presbyterian College, 1974; consultation on multi-generational education (Box 61)
  - St. Anselm's College Department of Nursing Education, 1966-1970; faculty development workshops (Box 61)
  - Saint Dunstan's Episcopal Church, New perspectives on adult education in the church, 1974 (Box 61)
  - St. Eulalia Rectory, 5th anniversary parish workshop, 1971 (Box 61)
  - Scarritt College Center of Continuing Education
    - Self-directed learning workshop, 1976 (Box 61)
  - Sherbrooke University Medical School, Andragogy self-directed and contract learning, 1977-1978 (Box 61)
  - Simon Rodriguez University, 1977; andragogy workshop (Box 61)
  - South Florida Inservice Educators, Techniques of adult education, 1971 (Box 62)
  - Southeastern Baptist Theological Seminary, Self-directed learning, 1977 (Box 62)
  - Southern Regional Education Board, Planning of in-service workshops, 1971 (Box 62)
  - State University of New York (SUNY) at Stony Brook-Health Sciences Center School of Allied Health Professions, Inservice program, techniques and resources for teaching health occupations education, 1974 (Box 62)
  - Stouffer Corporation
    - Hotel management candidate program, 1981 (Box 62)
    - Staff development and training, 1980-1981 (Box 62)
  - Temple University Hospital, 1967; nursing staff development program (Box 62)
  - Tennessee State University, 1st adult basic education workshop, 1970 (Box 62)
  - Toronto, Canada Board of Education
    - Inservice education workshop, 1970 (Box 62)
    - Leadership development program, 1971-1973 (Box 62)
  - United States Department of Agriculture Federal Extension Service
    - National home management workshop, 1960 (Box 62)
    - Workshop on creative procedures and processes in staff development to do 4-H work, 1974 (Box 62)
  - United States Department of Health, Education, and Welfare
    - National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH), Continuing education program development, 1971 (Box 62)
    - Regional staff development workshops, 1967-1968 (Box 62)
    - Social and Rehabilitation Service, Manpower development and training specialists, 1971 (Box 62)
  - United States Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD), 1968; training of trainers (Box 62)
  - United States Postal Service, Management intern sensitivity training program, 1968 (Box 62)
  - University of Chicago Department of Education, 10th annual summer workshop on family planning, 1972 (Box 62)
  - University of Connecticut School of Social Work, 1970-1971; continuing education services training sessions (Box 62)
  - University of Denver Law Center, Institute for court management, 1971 (Box 63)
  - University of Georgia School of Social Work, 1974; faculty retreat (Box 63)
  - University of Iowa College of Dentistry, 1977; faculty retreat (Box 63)
  - University of Kentucky, Kentucky Association of Continuing Education, and Southeastern Library Association, 1975; workshops (Box 63)
  - University of Manitoba, Master of Continuing Education program, 1972 (Box 63)
  - University of Maryland School of Social Work and Community Planning
    - Learning/teaching contracts workshop, 1975 (Box 63)
    - Teaching and learning in the university, 1974 (Box 63)